Are you one of the many who dreams of becoming a data scientist?
Keep watching this video if you're passionate about data science because we will tell you
how does the dream work under the hood?
Am I as a data scientist?
Let's see how a day in a life course while she's working on a data science project.
Well, it is very important to understand the business problem first.
In our meeting with the clients,
Am I asked relevant questions?
Understands and defines objectives for the problem that needs to be tackled?
She's a cutest soul who asks a lot of advice.
One of the many traits of a good data scientist.
Now, she cares up for data acquisition.
To gather and scrape data from multiple sources like web servers,
logs, databases, APIs, and online depositories.
Oh, it seems like finding the right data takes both time and effort.
After the data is gathered, come data preparation.
This step involves data cleaning and data transformation.
Data cleaning is the most time consuming process as it involves handling many complex scenarios.
Here, Am I dealing with inconsistent data types,
miss failed attributes, missing values, duplicate values, and whatnot.
Then, in data transformation, she modifies the data based on defined mapping rules.
In a project, ETL tools like talent and infamatica are used to perform complex transformations
that helps the team to understand the data structure better.
Then, understanding what you actually can do with your data is very crucial.
For that, Am I does exploratory data analysis?
With the help of EDA, she defines and defines the selection of feature labels that will be used in the
model development. But what if Am I skip step? She might end up choosing the wrong way to
use which will produce an inaccurate model. Does exploratory data analysis becomes the most
important step. Now, she proceeds to the core activity of a data science project.
Which is data modeling. She will rapidly apply type 4 machine learning techniques like
Canon, decision tree, knife base, to the data to identify the model that best fits the business requirement.
She trains the models on the training data set and test them to select the best performing model.
Am I prefers Python for modeling the data?
However, it can also be done using R and SAS.
Well, the trickiest part is not yet over. Visualization and communication.
Am I made the clients again to communicate with business findings in a simple and effective
manner to convince the stakeholders? She uses tools like Tablo, Power BI and ClickView.
That can help her in creating powerful reports and dashboards.
And then finally, she deploys and maintains the model. She tests the selected model in a pre-production
environment before deploying it in the production environment. This is the best practice right?
After successfully deploying it, she uses reports and dashboards to get real-time analytics.
Further, she also monitors and maintains the projects performance.
Well, that's how Emma completes the data science project.
We have seen the daily routine of a data scientist is a whole lot of fun, has a lot of interesting
aspects and comes with its own share of challenges. Now, let's see how data science is
changing the world. Data science techniques along with genomic data provide a deeper understanding
of genetic issues in reaction to particular drugs and diseases. Logistic companies like DHL,
FedEx, have discovered the best rules to ship the best suited time to deliver.
The best mode of transport to choose does leading to cost efficiency.
With data science, it is possible to not only predict employee attrition,
but to also understand the key variables that influence employee turnover.
Also, the airline companies can now easily predict flight delay and notify the passengers
beforehand to enhance their travel experience. Well, if you're wondering, there are various rules
offered to a data scientist. Like data analyst, machine learning engineer, deep learning engineer,
data engineer, and of course data scientists. The median base salaries of the data scientists
can range from $95,000 to $165,000. So that was about the data science. I already
did a data scientist. If yes, then start today. The world of data needs you. That's all from my
side today. Thank you for watching. Comment below the next topic that you want to learn and
subscribe to simply learn to get the latest updates on more such interesting videos. Thank you
and keep learning.