Hello and welcome to this session on data science with Python.
So what are we going to do in this session?
We will talk about what is data science and some of the basics of Python as you may be
aware data science.
We use either Python or R as some of the tools and programming languages.
So this session, the focus is on Python.
So we will talk about the basics of Python, white-alone Python, how to install Python.
And then we will talk about some of the important libraries which are required for data analysis.
And then we will go into a little bit of details about exploratory data analysis.
And we will take an example there of loan prediction.
And we will see a little bit about data wrangling using pandas, which is one of the libraries of Python.
And then we will end up with small predictive model or logistic regression model, which
is part of machine learning.
And in case you need more details about machine learning in this session, we will probably
not go into the details of machine learning.
There is a separate session.
You might want to look at.
There is a separate video on machine learning.
You might want to take a look at that.
If you need more details, here we are just giving a quick overview to see how we can use
the psychic learn library.
So we will not go into a lot of details about the basics of machine learning.
All right.
So with that, let's move forward.
So what is data science?
Data science is about finding insights from the data.
So if there is a lot of data, if you have sufficient data, how to analyze and find some insights
out of it, this is what is data science all about.
A couple of examples here, customer prediction.
Now let's say you have a customer base.
And you want to find out who are most likely to buy your product.
So you can use from your past behavior.
You can probably develop a model and try to predict who are the people out of the
thousand leads or potential customers who will actually buy.
So there may be some patterns that you can use to print it.
Similarly, service planning.
So for example, you're running a restaurant and you want to know how many people will
be coming or how many customers will be visiting your restaurant or even day.
Now based on your historical data, you can build a model to predict that as well.
So that there is no wastage of food and so on and so forth.
So these are very quick and easy examples of how data science can be used in business.
Now let's talk about Python.
For doing data science, we need some kind of a programming language or a tool and so on.
So this session will be about Python.
There are other tools like for example, R and we will probably do a separate video on that.
And the session is on Python and you must have already heard Python is really becoming very
popular.
Everybody is talking about Python, not only data science in IoT and AI in many other places.
So it's a very popular getting very popular.
So if you are not yet familiar with Python, this may be a good time to get started with it.
So why do we want to use Python?
So basically, Python is used as a programming language because it is for data science because
it has some rich tools from mathematics and from a statistical perspective.
It has some rich tools.
So that is one of the reasons why we use Python.
And if you see some of the trends, if you're probably tracking some of the trends,
you will see that over the last few years, Python has become programming language of choice.
And especially for data science,
says was earlier one of the most popular tools.
But now increasingly, Python is being used for doing data science.
And of course, as well as R.
One of the reasons, of course, is that Python and R are open source,
compared to SAS, which is a commercial product.
So that could definitely be one explanation.
But beyond that, I think it is the ease of understanding this language,
the ease of using this language, which is also making it very popular.
In addition to the availability of fantastic libraries for performing data science.
What are the other factors?
There are speed, then there are availability of number of packages.
And then of course, the design goal.
All right.
So what are each of these design goals?
Primarily, the syntax rules in Python are relatively intuitive.
And easy to understand.
They're by it helps in building applications with the concise and readable code
base.
So it's a few lines of code.
You can really achieve a lot of stuff.
And then there are a lot of packages that are available that have been developed
by other people, which can be reused.
So we don't have to reinvent the wheel.
And last but not least, speed.
So Python is relatively faster language.
Of course, it is not as fast as, let's say, CFC++.
But then relatively, it is still faster.
So these are the three factors, which may Python the programming language of choice.
So if you want to get started with Python, first thing obviously is to install Python.
So there is some documentation.
And there are some steps that you need to follow.
So we will try to briefly touch upon that.
Otherwise, of course, there is a lot of material available on how to install Python.
So on, you can always look around.
But this is one of the game.
There are different ways in which you can also install Python.
So we will use the anaconda path.
There is a packaging tool called anaconda.
So we will use that path.
You can also directly install Python.
But in our session, we will use the anaconda route.
So the first thing you need to do is download anaconda.
And this is the path for that.
And once you click on this, you will come to a page somewhat like this.
And download, you can do the corresponding download based on whether you have a windows or
Ubuntu.
There is also a download possible for a package available for Ubuntu if you're doing something
on Ubuntu.
So based on which operating system.
In fact, this page will automatically detect which operating system you're having.
And it will actually suggest.
So for example, you see here, if you're running macOS, then it will automatically detect
that you have macs and the corresponding installers will be displayed here.
Similarly, if you're on some flavor of linux, like Ubuntu or any other, then you will get
the corresponding download links here.
And then beyond that, you can also select which version of Python you want to install.
Of course, the latest version is in the 3.x range at the time of recording.
This 3.6 is one of the latest versions.
But some of you may want to do or start with the earlier version, which is Python 2.7 to
.text.
And you can download that as well.
If you don't have anything installed, then my suggestion is start with Python 3.6.
All right.
So once you do that, you will be able to install Python and you will be able to run
Jupiter notebook.
Okay.
So now that you know how to install Python and you if you have installed Python, let's
take a look at what are the various libraries that are available.
So Python is a very easy language to learn.
And there are some basic stuff that you can do.
For example, adding, operating a hollow world statement and so on without importing any
specific libraries.
But if you want to perform data analysis, you need to include or import some specific libraries.
So we are going to talk about those as we move forward.
So pandas, for example, is used for structured data operation.
So if you let's say are performing something on a CSV file, you import a CSV file,
create a data frame.
And then you can do a lot of stuff like data munching and data preparation before you do any
other stuff like for example, machine learning or so on.
So that's pandas.
Side pie as the name suggests, it is kind of it provides more scientific capabilities.
Like for example, it has linear algebra, it has Fourier transform and so on and so forth.
Then you have NumPy which is a very powerful library for performing and dimensional or creating
and dimensional arrays.
And it also has some of the stuff that is there in sci-fi.
Like for example, linear algebra and Fourier transform and so on and so forth.
Then you have MATLAB which is primarily for visualization purpose.
It has again very powerful features for visualizing your data for doing the initial
what is known as exploratory data analysis for doing univariate analysis by variate analysis.
So this is extremely useful for visualizing the data.
And then sci-kit learn is used for performing all the machine learning activities.
If you want to do anything like linear regression classification or any of this stuff that the
sci-kit learn library will be extremely helpful.
In addition to that, there are a few other libraries for example, networks and
I graph.
Then of course a very important one is tens of love.
So if you are interested in doing some deep learning or AI related stuff, then it would be
a good idea to learn about tens of love and tens of lies one of the libraries.
There is a separate video on tens of love you can look for that.
And this is one of the libraries created by Google open source library.
So once your familiar with machine learning data analysis machine learning them,
that may be the next step to go to deep learning and AI.
So that's where tens of love will be used.
Then you have beautiful soup which is the primarily used for web scraping and then you take
the data and then analyze and so on.
Then OS libraries are very common libraries.
The name suggests it is for operating system.
So if you want to do something on creating directories or folders and things like that,
that's when you would use OS.
All right.
So moving on.
Let's talk in a little bit more detail about each of these libraries.
So sci-fi as the name suggests is a scientific library and it very specifically,
it has some special functions of our integration and for ordinary differential equation.
So as you can see these are mathematical operations or mathematical functions.
So these are already available in this library and it has linear algebra modules and it is built
on top of NumPy.
So you'll see what is there in NumPy.
So this is again as the name suggests that Num comes from Numbers.
So it is a mathematical library and one of its key features is availability of an
and dimensional array of checked.
It is a very powerful object and we will see how to use this and then of course you can create
other let's objects and so on.
And it has tools for integrating with CC++ and also for transcode and then it of course also has
linear algebra and Fourier transformation and so on all these scientific capabilities.
Okay.
What else pandas is another very powerful library primarily for data manipulation.
So if you're importing any files you will want to create it like a table.
So you will create what is known as data frames.
These are very powerful data structures that are used in Python programming.
So pandas library provides this capability and once you import a data import the data into data
frame you can pretty much do whatever you're doing like in a regular database.
So people who are coming from a database background or SQL background would really like this
because it is very difficult field very much at home because it feels like you're using your
viewing a table or using a table and you can do a lot of stuff using the pandas library.
Now there are two important terms or components in pandas series and a data frame.
I was just talking about the data frame.
So let's take a look at what are series and what is a data frame.
So within pandas we have series and data frames.
So series is primarily some of you may also be knowing this as let's say an array.
So it's a one-dimensional structure.
Data structure if you will.
So in some other languages you may call it as an array or maybe some of the probably any
cool and awful list.
I mean, are perhaps I'm not very sure on that aspect but yes.
So this is like a one-dimensional storage of information.
So that is what a series.
Whereas data frame is like a table.
So you have a two-dimensional structure.
You have rows and you have columns and this is very people.
As I said, we're familiar with SQL and databases.
We'll be able to relate to this very quickly.
So you have like a table, you have rows and columns and then you can manipulate the data.
So if you want to create a series, this is how you would create a code snippet.
And as you can see, the programming in Python is very simple.
There are no major overheads.
You just need to import some libraries, whichever essential.
And then start creating objects.
So you don't have to do additional declaration of variables and things like that.
So that is a think one key difference between Python and other programming languages.
And what does this series contain?
It has to contain these numbers, 6346 and X is my object consisting of the series.
So if you display, if you just say X, it will display the contents of X.
And you will see here that it creates a default index.
Then you have data frames.
So if you want to create a data frame, as you can see, the series is like a one-dimensional structure.
There is just like a row, one row of items.
Whereas a data frame looks somewhat like this.
It is a two-dimensional structure.
So you have columns and one dimension and then you have rows in the other dimension.
How do you create a data frame?
You need to create a unique rather import pandas.
And then you import.
In this case, we are basically creating our own data.
So that's the reason we are importing NumPy, which is one of the libraries.
We just refer to a little bit before.
So we are using one of the functionalities within NumPy to create some random numbers.
So otherwise this is not really mandatory.
You probably will be importing the data from outside.
Maybe some CSV file and import into the data frames.
So that's what we are doing here.
So in this case, we are creating our own test data.
That's the reason we are importing NumPy as NP.
And then I create a data frame saying PD.datafram.
So this is the keyword here.
Similarly here in this case, while creating series, we set PD.series.
And then you pass the value.
Similarly here, using PD.datafram.
Now in order to create the data frame, it needs the values in each of these cells.
What are the values in the rows?
And what are the values in the columns?
So that in our example, we are providing using this random number generator.
So NP.datandam is like a class or a method that is available in NumPy.
And then you're saying, it generates some random numbers in the form of a 4 by 3 matrix
or 4 by 3 data frame.
The 4 here indicates the number of rows.
And the 3 here indicates the number of columns.
So these are the columns 0, 1, 2 are the columns.
And these are the rows.
Here 0, this is 1, this is 2, this is 3.
And once again, it will when you display a DF,
it will give us a default index.
There are ways to omit that, but at this point, we will just keep it simple.
So it will display the default index and then the actual values in each of these rows.
And column.
So this is the way you create a data frame.
So now that we have learned some of the basics of pandas, let's take a quick look at how we
use this in real life.
So let's assume we have a situation where we have some customer data.
And we want to kind of predict whether a customer's loan will be approved or not.
So we have some historical data about the loans and about the customers.
And using that, we will try to come up with a way to maybe predict whether
loan will be approved or not.
So let's see how we can do that.
So this is a part of exploratory analysis.
So we will first start with exploratory analysis.
We will try to see how the data is looking.
So what kind of data?
So we will of course I'll take you into the Jupiter notebook and give you a quick live demo.
But before that, let's quickly walk through some of the pieces of this program in slides.
And then I will take you actually into the actual code and do a demo of that.
So the Python program structure looks somewhat like this.
The first step is to import your all the required libraries.
Now of course it is not necessary that you have to import all your libraries right at the top of the
code. But it is a good practice.
So if you know you are going to need a certain set of libraries.
It may be a good idea to put from a readability perspective.
It's a good practice to put all the libraries that you're importing at the beginning of your code.
However, it is not mandatory.
So in the middle of the code somewhere if you feel that you need a particular library,
you can import that library and then start using it in the middle of the code.
So that's also perfectly fine.
It will not give any error.
So anything?
However, as I said, it's not such a good practice.
So we will import all the required libraries.
In this case, we are importing pandas, numpy and matplotlib.
And in addition, if we include this piece of code,
percentage matplotlib in line, what will happen is all the graphs that we are going to create.
The visualizations that we are going to create will be displayed within the notebook.
So if you want to have that kind of a provision, you need to have this line.
So it's always a good idea when you're starting off.
I think it's a good idea to just include this line so that your graphs are shown in line.
Okay. So these are the four.
We will start with these four lines of code.
Then the next step is to import your data.
So in our case, there is a training data for loans by the name loan, p underscore train.csv.
And we are reading this data.
So in this case, you see, unlike the previous example, where we created a data frame with some
data that we created ourselves, here we are actually creating a data frame using some external
data. And it's the method is very, very straightforward.
So you use the read underscore CSV method.
And it is a very intuitive function name.
And you say, pd dot read underscore CSV and give the path of the file CSV file.
That's about it. And then that is ready to the data frame df.
This can be any name. We are calling it df. You can call xyz.
Anything. This is a name. Just name of the object.
So head is one of the methods within the data frame.
And it will give us the first five.
So this is just to take a quick look. Now you have imported the data.
You want to initially have a quick look. How your data is looking.
What are the values in some of the columns and so on and so forth?
So typically you would do a head df dot head to get the sample of let's say the first few lines
of your data. So that's what has happened here. So it displays the first few lines.
And then you can see what are the columns within that and what are the values in each of these
cells and so on and so forth. You can also typically you would like to see there are any null values.
Sorry, are there any is the data for whatever reason is invalid or looking dirty for whatever
reason some unnecessary character. So this will give a quick view of that. So in this case,
pretty much everything looks okay. Then the next step is to understand the data a little bit
overall for each of the columns. What is the information? So the describe function will basically
give us a summary of the data. What else can we do? Pandas also allows us to visualize the data
and this is more like a part of what we call it as univariate analysis. That means each and every
column you can take and do some plots and visualization to understand data in each of the columns.
So for example, here the loan amount column we can take and then the hist basically hist method
will create a histogram. So you take all the values from one column which is low amount and you
create a histogram to see how the data is distributed. So that's what is happening here and as you
can see there are some extreme values. So this is again to identify do we have to do some data
preparation because if the data is in a completely haphazard way the analysis may be difficult.
So with these are the initial or exploratory data analysis, this is primarily done to understand
that and see if we need to do some data preparation before we get into the other steps like
machine learning and statistical modeling and so on. So in this case we will see that here by plotting
this histogram we see that there are some extreme values. So there are some values. A lot of it is
around 100 range but there is also something or one or two observations in the 700 range. So it's
pretty scattered in that sense or there are not really scattered. Distributed at least scattered
but it is randomly scattered. So the range is really huge. So what can we do about it? So there
are some steps that we need to do normalization and so on. So we'll see that in a bit. So this is
for one of the columns. Let's take another column which is applicant income. Similar kind of similar
situation you have most of your observations in this range but there are also some which are far off
from very most of the observations are. So this is also pretty this also has some extreme values.
So we love to see what can be done. Credit history is the binary value. So some people have a zero
value and some will have credit history of one. This is just like a flag. So this basically is telling
us how many people have a one and how many people have zero. So it looks like majority of them
have a value of one and a few about 100 of them have a value of zero. Okay. What else can we do?
So we now understood a little bit about the data. So we need to do some data rangling or data
munging and see if we can some bring in some kind of normalization of all this data. And
we will kind of try to understand what is data rangling and before we actually go into it. Okay.
So data rangling is nothing but a process of cleaning the data. If let's say there are
there are multiple things that can happen. In this particular example there were no missing values.
But typically when you get some data very often it will so happen that a lot of values are missing.
Either they are null values or there are a lot of zeros. Now you cannot use such data as it is
to perform some let's say predictive analysis or perform some machine learning activities and so on.
So that is one part of it. So you need to clean the data. The other is unifying the data. Now
these ranges of this data are very huge. Some of them are going from some columns are going from
zero to over a thousand and some columns are just between 10 to 20 and so on. These will affect
the accuracy of the analysis. So we need to do some kind of unifying the data and so on. So that
is what rangling data rangling is all about. So before we actually perform any analysis we need to
bring the data so to some kind of a shape so that we can perform additional analysis. Actually
analysis on this and get some insights. Now how do we deal with missing values? There's a very
common issue when we take data or when we get data from the business. When a data scientist gets
a data from the business. So we should never assume that all our data will be clean and all the
values filled up and so on because in real life very often there will be the data will be dirty.
So data rangling is the process where you kind of clean up the data. First of all identify whether
the data is dirty and then clean up. So how do we find some data is missing? So there are a few ways
you can write a small piece of code which will identify a for a given column or for given
row any of the observations are null primarily. So this line of code for example is doing that.
It is trying to identify how many null values or missing values are there for each of the columns.
So this is a lambda function and what we are saying is find out a for value is null and then
you add all of them. How many observations are there where it is particular column is null.
So it does that for all the column. So here you will see that for low 90 obviously it's an id.
So there are no null values or missing values. Gender has about 13 observations where the value
is missing. Similarly, marital status has three and so on and so forth. So we will see here for
example of low n amount has 21 observations where the value is missing, low n amount term has
14 observations and so on. So we will see how to handle this missing values. So there are multiple
ways in which you can handle missing values. If the number of observations are very small compared
to the total number of observations then sometimes one of the easy ways is to completely remove
that data. So or delete that record exclude that record. So that is one way of doing it.
So if there are let's say a million records and maybe 10 records are having missing values.
It may not be worth doing something to fill up those values. It may be better off to get
rid of those observations. So that is the missing values are proportionately very small.
But if there are relatively large number of missing values, if you exclude those observations then
your accuracy may not be that very good. So there are the other way of doing it as we can take
a mean value of a particular column and fill up wherever there are missing values. Fill up those
observations or cells with the mean value. So that way what happens is you don't give some value
which is too high or too low and it somehow fits within the range of observations that we are seeing.
So this is one technique. Again, there are it can be case to case and you may have to take a
call based on your specific situation. But these are some of the common method. If you see in the
previous case, low and amount had 21 and now we went ahead and filled all of those with the mean value.
So now there are zero with missing values. So this is one part of a data wrangling activity.
What else you can do? You can also check what are the types of the data. So DF dot
the types will give us what are the various data types. So all right. So you can also perform some
basic mathematical observations. We have already seen that mean reform now. So similarly, if you do
call the mean method for the data frame object, it will actually perform or display or calculate
the mean for pretty much all the numerical columns that are available in this. Right. So for example,
here we can come co-ocult, content and come and all these are numerical values. So it will display
the mean values of all of those. Now another thing that you can do is you can actually also
combine data frame. So let's say you import data from one CSV file into one data frame and
another CSV file into another data frame and then you want to merge these because you want to do
an analysis on entire data. One example could be that you have data in the form of CSV files,
one CSV file for each month of the year. Generally, February, March, each of these are in a different.
So you can import them into let's say 12 data frames and then you can merge them together as a single
data frame and then you perform your analysis on the entire data frame or the entire data for the
year. So that is one example. So how do we do that? This is our video. Again, in this case, we are not
importing any data. We are just creating some random values or using some random values. So let's
assume I have a data frame which is by the name 1 and I assign some random values here.
Which is a 5 by 4 format. So there are 5 rows and 4 columns and this is our my data frame 1 looks.
And then I create another data frame which is data frame 2 again random numbers of the format 5 by 4
and I have something like this. Now I want to combine these two. How do I combine these two?
I can use the concatenate or concatenate method and I can combine these two. So pd.concate
and it takes the the data frames 1 and 2. If you have more of them, you can provide them and it will just
simply add all of them merge all of them. For concatenate, whatever you call whichever term you call,
it will. So of course, we have to make sure that the structure remains the same. Like I said,
this could be let's say sales data coming for 12 different months. But each of the files has the same
structure. So now you can combine all of them. More Jol of them are using the concatenate method.
If we have let's say structure is not identical, then what will happen? Let's say we have these two
data frames. One has a column by the name key and the second column is L.Veal and a second data
frame which has a column by the name key. But the second column by the name are well not L.Veal.
So you see here the structure is not identical. So you can still combine them. But then the way they
get combined or merged is somewhat like this. So it takes the key as a common parameter between them.
Some common column has to be there otherwise this will not work. And then we have to use merge
instead of concatenate. And when we do a merge, then we get the result will be in this format.
What it does is it uses the key as a common thread between them. And then it kind of populates the
values accordingly. So if you see here the first one had four and bar for key and then it had
L values of one and two. So if we go back four and bar had one and two L value. So that's what we see
here one and two. Whereas in the right data frame we had four bar and bar is a second time and then
R values are three four and five. So what it has done for four it has put for the existing right
four is already existing because it has come from left. So it will just put the value of R value here.
Which is three. Similarly it will put four here because for bar if you go back for bar it is
the value is four. And since it has one more value of bar it will go and add this five as well.
The only thing here is that this one had for example left had only two values and only one value
for bar but since we are depending on merging and there are two key values with the bar.
Therefore it will kind of repeat the value of L value here. So that's what we are seeing in this case.
So L value appears twice the number two appears twice but that is because R value there are two of them.
All right. So that is how when you don't have identical structure that's of you merge.
Now we will talk a little bit about cyclotler. So cyclotler is a library which is used for doing
machine learning of for performing machine learning activities. So if you want to do linear regression
logistic regression and so on there are easily usable APIs that you can call and that's
the advantage of cyclotler. And it provides a bunch of algorithms. So I think that is the
put part about this library. So if you want to use cyclotler obviously you need to import these
modules and also there are some sub modules you may have to import based on what you're trying to
use. For example if we know if we want to use logistic regression. Again people who are probably
not very familiar with machine learning there is a separate module for machine learning you may
want to take a look at that but we will just touch upon the basics here. So machine learning has
algorithms like linear regression logistic regression and random forest classification and so on.
So that is what we are talking about here. So those algorithms are available and when if you want to
use some of them you need to import them and from the cyclotler library. So cyclotler is the top
level library which is basically a still learn right and then it has kind of sub parts in it.
You need to import those based on what exactly you will be or which algorithm you will be using.
So let's take an example as we move and we will see that whenever we perform some machine learning
activity those of you who are familiar with machine learning will already know this we split our
labeled data into two parts training and test. Now there are multiple ways of splitting this data
how do we either some people do it like 5050 some people do it 8020 which is training is 80 and
20 and so on. So it is individual preference. There are no hard and fast rules.
By and large we have seen that training data set is larger than the test data set and again
we will probably not go into details of why do we do this at this point but that's one of the steps
in machine learning. So cyclotler offers a readily available method to do this which is train test
split. So in this example let's say we are taking the values x and y are our values.
x is the independent variables and y is our dependent variable and we are using these two and then
I want to split this into train and test data. So what do we do? We import the train test split
sub module from within psychic learn which is a scalar right. So within that we import train test
split and then you call the strain test split method or function or whatever you call that
and pass the data. So x is the all the values of the independent variables and y is our labels.
So you pass x and y and then you specify what should be your size of the test data. So only one
you need to specify. So if you say test size is 0.25 it is understood that train size will be 0.75.
So you're telling what should be the ratio of this split. So technically it doesn't
nothing prevents you from giving whatever you like here. So you can give test as 80 and train as
20. So whichever way but then there's normal practices you will have the training data set would be larger
than the test data set and typically it would be 80 to 20 75 25 or 65 35 something like that.
So that is the second parameter and this is just to say that you know the data has to be randomly
split. So it shouldn't be like you take the first 75% and put it in training and then the next
25% and put it in test so that so such a thing shouldn't happen. So we first set the state random
state so that the splitting is done in a very random way. So if they randomly picked up the data
and then put it into training and test and then this results in these four data frames. So x
train and x test and y train and y test. Okay. So that is basically the result it will
start. Now that the splitting is done let's see how to implement or execute logistic regression.
So in logistic regression what we try to do is try to develop a model which will classify
the data. Logistic regression is an algorithm for supervised learning for performing classification.
So logistic regression is for classification and usually it is binary classification. So binary
classification means there are two classes. So either like a yes no or for example customer will buy
or will not buy. So that is a binary classification. So that's where we use logistic regression.
So let's take a look at the code how to implement something like that using scikit-learn.
So the first thing is to import this logistic regression sub-module or sub-class whatever you call it
and then create an instance of that. So our object is classifier. So we are creating an object by the name.
This is a name by the way you can give any name in our case we are saying classifier.
We say classifier is equal to logistic regression. So we are creating an instance of the logistic
regression variable or class or whatever. Okay and you can pass a variable or a parameter rather
which is the random state is equal to zero. And once you create the object which in our case is
named classifier you can then train the object by calling the method fit. So this is important to
not we don't call any there is no method like train here but we call what is known as there is a
method called fit. So you are basically by calling the fit method you are training this model.
And in order to train the model you need to pass the training data set. So x underscore train is
your independent variables the set of independent variables and y underscore train is your dependent
variable or the label. So you pass both of these and call the fit function of it method which will
actually result in the training of this model classifier. Now this is basically showing what are the
possible parameters that can be passed or initiated when we are calling the logistic or the
instance of logistic regression. So this is what you can also look up the health file if you have
installed Python. So some of these are very intuitive but some you may want to take a look at the
details of what exactly they do. All right so moving on once we train the model by calling fit
then the next step is to test our model. So this is where we will use the test data unit
pay attention here. Here I am calling so there are two things. One is in order to test our data we have
to actually call what is known as the method known as predict. So here this is where so the training is
done now is the time for inference isn't it? So we have the model. Now we want to check whether our
model is working correctly or not. So what you do you have your test data remember we split it
25% of our data was stored here right we split it into test and training. So that 25% of the data
we pass to and call the method predict so that the model will now predict a values for y right so that's
why here we are calling it as y and score predict and if we display here as I said this is a logistic
regression which is basically binary classification. So it gives us the results like yes or no
in this particular case and then you can so this is what the model has predicted or model has classified.
Now but we also know we already have the labels for this. So we need to compare with existing labels
with the known labels whether this classification is correct or not. So that is where is the next
step which is basically calculating the accuracy and so on will come into play. Okay so in this case the
first thing most important thing to notice we do the prediction using predict and here we are passing
x and is called test and not trained right in this case we did x and y. So again one more point
to be noted here in case of training we will pass both the independent variables and also the
dependent variables because the system has to internally it has to verify that is what is the
training process. So what it will do it will take the x values it will try to come up with the y value
and compare with the actual y value right so that is what is the training method so that's why we have
to pass both x as well as y whereas in case of predict we don't pass both we only pass because we
are pretending as if this is the actual data so in actual data you will not have the labels isn't it?
So we are just passing the independent variables and the system will then come up with the y values
which we will then remember we also know the actual values so we will compare this with the actual
values and we will find out whether how accurate the model is. So how do we do that?
We use what is known as a confusion matrix so this is also readily available in the Python library
so we import this confusion matrix and some of you who already know machine learning will find
this familiar but those who are new to machine learning this confusion matrix is nothing but this
matrix this kind of a matrix which basically tells how many of them are correctly predicted
and how many of them are incorrectly predicted so the some of the characteristics let's quickly
spend some time on this confusion matrix itself this the total numbers out here these are just the
numbers these are like number of observations then the accuracy is considered to be highest when the
the numbers or the sum of the numbers across the diagonals is maximum okay and the numbers
outside of the diagonal should be minimum so which means that if this model was 100% accurate
then the sum of these two there would have been only numbers in these two along the diagonal this would
have been 0 and this would have been 0 okay so that is like a 100% accurate model that is very rare
but just that you are aware so it's just a given idea okay all right so once you have the confusion
matrix you then try to calculate the accuracy which is in a percentage so there are two things
that we can do from a confusion matrix or that we can calculate from a confusion matrix one is the
accuracy and the other is the precision what is the accuracy accuracy is basically a measure of how many
of the observations have been correctly predicted okay so let's say this is a little bit more
detailed view of the confusion matrix it looks very similar like as we saw in this case right
so this is a 2 by 2 matrix that's what we are seeing here 18 27 21 0 3 so 18 27 21 0 3 now but
what are these values that is what is the kind of the labels are shown here in this so there are all
together 150 observations so as I said the sum of all these four right 18 plus 27 plus 103 plus 2
is equal to 150 that's the first thing we have to observe the sum of all these values will be equal
to the sum of test observations number of test observations we have 150 test observations because
remember we had about 500 we split that into 25 75 so that is why we have 150 here and I think 350
in the training data set okay so that we get the numbers correct so that's the first thing now this
next thing is let's take a look at the actual values this view is the actual view so there are actually
right in the actual data we have labels yes and no so as per the actual data there are 45
observations tagged as no and similarly there are 105 observations that are tagged as yes or labeled as
yes okay now I know for the first time when you're seeing this it may be a little confusing but just
stay with me okay so this is the actual part of it and this side tells us the predicted part of it
so our model has predicted and it has totally predicted 20 of them as no right so that is what this
is totally 20 of them it has predicted as no and it has predicted 130 of them as yes okay I hope
this part is clear so before we go into the middle part let us first understand what exactly are these
numbers so actually tagged as no there are 45 total actually tagged as yes there are 105 and predicted
no there are 20 predicted as yes there are 130 this is the result from our model okay this is the
result from our model and this is the actual value which we already know because this is our label data
that is the first thing now now let us take a look at each of these individually okay now what
are the options we have on the game okay so now what is happening here let us look at these these values
so this 18 says that these are actually tagged as no and the model has also predicted as no which
means this is what is known as a true positive right or true negative sorry right which means that
our model has predicted is it correctly it is negative because it says no so and it is also predicted
no so it is known as what is known as true negative okay now let us come to this side of it that way
we are talking about the diagonal remember I said most of the value should be in the diagonal okay
so that means these 18 are correctly tagged they are labeled as no and our model has predicted as no
so these are correctly tagged and these are known as true negative okay similarly if we come
diagonally down there are 103 observations which are labeled as yes actual value is as and our
model has also predicted as yes and these are known as true positive values positive because of this
yes okay right so what is important is this is true this is also true so we have to make sure that
the maximum number of values are in the true section okay true positive and true negative that's the
reason I said the sum along the diagonal should be maximum now let's say your our model was 100%
accurate this sum in this case it is only 103 plus 103 plus 18 which is 21 but if our model
was accurate the sum of these two would have been 150 that means it's a perfect model okay all right
what else since we covered these two let's also cover these two so here this says that 27 of them
we're actually labeled no but our model has predicted as yes that means this is wrong right
similarly these are two of them where the actual value is yes but our model has predicted as no
that means it's a wrong prediction so you get the point so therefore along the diagonals are the
correct values whereas in other places it is all wrong values or wrong predictions okay now how do we
calculate accuracy from this information so the way to calculate accuracy is so we'd say okay there are
total observations are 150 and what are the correctly predicted values these are the correctly
predicted values which is 18 plus 103 so this will give us our accuracy so 103 plus 18 which is
121 divided by our total observations which is 150 is our accuracy which is 0.8 or we can say it is
80% okay now there is another concept called precision so precision is given by the formula
true positives divided by the predicted positives totally predicted positives okay what do we mean by
that which are the true positives here remember which are the true positives we just recall we just
talked in the previous slide which are the true positives you see here so this 103 are the true positives
which means that the value is positive actual value is positive predicted values also positive so that's
what's called a true positive so 103 divided by so that is our true positive 103 divided by
totally predicted as yes now what is totally predicted as yes it remember 130 of them I have all
together been predicted as yes not that they're correctly predicted only 103 have been correctly
predicted but 130 of them have been predicted as yes so precision is basically the ratio of these two
out of the totally predicted how many of them are actually true that ratio so 103 by 130 which is
again about 80% is the precision that's how you calculate precision so this is just a simple formula
in the term that you need to remember so accuracy is you need to take total of true positive and true
negative divided by the total number of observations whereas precision is true positives divided
by the totally predicted positives okay so that is our accuracy and precision now what we did
the accuracy calculation was manual but we can also use some libraries which are already existing
and the functions within that library so a circuit learned provides one such method so for example
accuracy underscore score is one such method so if you use that and pass your test and predicted
values only the why you need to pass right the dependent variable values so if you pass that it will
calculate it for you so in this case again as you can see it still calculates the same which is 80
percent which we have seen here as well okay so this can be done using the method great so that's
pretty much what we have done here before we conclude let me take you into the code and show you
how it actually looks okay so this is our code let me run it okay one by one we have already seen
most of the steps and slides so I will but I will run this in the actual Jupiter node box some
of you if you are not yet familiar with Jupiter node book again there are other videos we created
on how to install Jupiter node book and how to set up Jupiter node book and so on in this tutorial
also we there was one slide on how to install python and Jupiter node book if you have not yet
done please do that so that then you can actually walk through this code while you are watching this okay
so what are we doing here we are importing the libraries required libraries we call here we have
pandas we have numpy and for visualization we have matplotlib and this line is basically reading
the CSV file so we have the CSV file locally on our local right and this is where I am checking
the data just so I am starting with max directory analysis how the data is looking so it looks good
I don't know major missing values or anything like that so it will display all the columns and
it will show me the first five rows if when I am using this head function and then I want to see
kind of a summary of all the each of the numerical columns so that's what I am doing here these are
the numerical columns and it gives a summary like how many observations are there what is the mean
standard deviation minimum maximum and so on and so forth for each of them and then you can
do some visualization so this is the visualization for this okay the next step is to view the data
visualization and we will do that using a histogram for a couple of these columns so in this case
I am taking a look at the low numhount and if I create a histogram it displays the data here
in the form of a histogram one thing that we gather from this as I mentioned in the slides as well
is how the data is kind of scattered so while most of the values are in this range 0 to 300
there are a few extreme values around the 700 range so that is one information we get from this
histogram similarly for the applicant income if we draw histogram something similar we can see
that while most of the values are in this range 0 to 20000 range there are a few in the range of
80000 and probably 65000 and so on okay so the next step is to perform data wrangling where we will
check if any data is missing and how to fill those missing values and so on so in this case we will
just check for all the columns how many data or how many entries are there with missing values this is
the results alone I did has all the columns are all the cells filled gender has 13 missing values
metal status has 3 missing values and so on and so forth low numhount has 21 and this is what we are
going to show you how to remove these missing values so when you have missing values as I mentioned
during the slides there are a couple of ways of handling that one is you can completely remove those
or you fill in with some meaningful values so in this case we will fill the missing values with the
main value of the low numhount so let's go ahead and do that and now if we check here now
low numhount number of missing values is 0 because what we did was for all these 21 cells where
the values were missing we filled with the main value of the low numhount so now there are no more
missing values for low numhount we can do this for other columns as well but this was just one
example so we have shown it here okay so we will run this for credit history and low numhount term
as well and then if we calculate the mean of pretty much all the numerical columns that's the
method called so DF dot mean will give us the mean of all the numerical values and another thing
that we can do is we if you want to find out what are the data types of each of these columns so you
can call DF dot D types and get the data types of course they may not be that very useful most of
the cases is an object but for example this one it shows as n64 and there are float 64 and so on and so
forth now in addition to doing the exploratory data analysis we can do some machine learning activity
as well so in this case we are going to do logistic regression so this is the example that I have
shown you in the slides as well this is the actual code for that all right so the first step here
is to import the libraries and then the next step is to separate the independent variables and
the dependent variables so x is our independent variable and y is our dependent variable so we separate
the data into two parts and this will be our target as well right so that's how we separated now
we have to split the data into training and test data sets as I mentioned in the during the slides
we use the train test click method and when we call this and pass the independent variables
and the dependent variables and we specify the test size to be 0.25 which means the training size
will be 0.75 which is nothing but you split the data into training data set which is 75%
and test data set in which is 25%. Okay so once you split that you will have all your independent
variables data in x train the training data which is 75% of it similarly independent variables for
test will be in x underscore test and dependent variables train will be in y underscore train
and dependent variable test will be y underscore test once we do this we have to do a small exercise
for scaling remember we had some data which was kind of very scattered there were some extreme
values and so on so this will take care of that so that the data is normalized so that before we
pass to our algorithm the data is normalized so that the performance will be much better.
The next step is to create the instance of logistic regression object so that's what we are doing here
so classifier is our logistic regression instance right classifier is equal to logistic regression
we are saying so one instance of logistic regression is created and then we call the training method
the name of the method actually is fit but what it is doing is it is taking the training data x is
the training data or the independent variables and y is the dependent variables so we are taking
both of these and the model gets trained so the method for calling the training is fit okay so it
gives us the output and then once we are done with the training we do the testing and once again just
to recall in the slides when I was showing you the slides also I mentioned we don't pass y here
while we are testing while for training we do pass y but right so for fit we are passing x and y
but for test we are only passing x something you need to observe because y will be calculated
by the model and we will then compare that with the known value of y to measure the accuracy so that's
what we will do here and the method that is called here is predict so this will basically create or predict
the values of y now we have in this case a binary classification so the outputs are yes or no
y indicates yes and then indicates no so y or n is the output now how do we measure the accuracy as
we have seen earlier I described how confusion matrix works and how we can use confusion matrix
for calculating accuracy that's what we are seeing here so this is the confusion matrix and then
you want to do the measure the accuracy you can directly use this method and we find that it is 80% so
we in the slides we have seen when we calculate manually as well we get an accuracy of 80%.
okay let's go back to our slides and do a summary so what we have done in the session we talked
about what is data science and y python is being used why it is becoming so popular how to install
python and we talked about the various libraries in python like pandas, scipy, nampai and so on
and then we took a couple of examples and wrote the code and demonstrated the code for performing
exploratory analysis and performing data rangling or data manipulation and then we at the end we
did one example of machine learning using scikit learn library and performed the logistic regression
examples so with that we come to the end of the session if you have any queries comments please put
them below and you can also give your email ID so that we can get back to you if you have any questions
I hope you enjoyed the session thank you very much.
Hi there if you like this video subscribe to the simple learning youtube channel and click here to
watch similar videos turn it up and get certified click here