See in this movie called Memento or the little ball of the movie called GUSNY.
Our basic RNNs are like the heroes of that movie.
They suffer from a short term memory problem.
LSTM is a special version of RNN which solves this short term memory problem.
And in this video I will explain LSTM in a very simple manner using real life examples.
Let's say you have NLP task for centers completion.
Here in both the sentences, based on what word appeared in the beginning,
your auto complete centers might be different. For example, for the first one,
I would say I need to take a loan, whereas for the second one, I would say I had to take a loan.
And this decision between need and head was made based on what appeared at the very beginning.
Now, looking at what traditional RNN architecture,
if you have seen my previous videos, you would know this is how RNN architecture looks like.
So if you are not seen those videos, I highly recommend you watch them because they are kind of a
prerequisite. Here, when you feel the sentence word by word, so first you will feel today.
It will learn some weights. There is an activation which is fed back.
Now you work on the second word which is due, then the third word which is two.
So this is how basic RNN works. If you enroll this thing in time,
then this is how the architecture will look like.
Many people get confused. The thing that this is a neural network with so many layers.
Actually, there is only one layer. Look at this time axis, T1, T2, T3.
So it's the same layer represented in different time and when you enroll it, this is how it looks.
Now to predict this word need, it needs to know about the word today, which appeared at the very beginning of the sentence.
And because of vanishing gradient problem, the traditional RNNs have short term memory.
So they don't remember what appeared in the beginning of the sentence.
They have a very short term memory of just few words which are like nearby.
Hence, to autocomplete this kind of sentence, RNN won't be able to do a good job.
Similarly, this is the second sentence, where head was derived based on the earlier word, which is last year.
Now let's look at the network layer a little more in detail.
So I'm going to just expand this particular network layer, which looks like this.
So there are set of neurons in that layer. And this hidden state is nothing but a short term memory.
So I'm just going to remove this neurons just to kind of make it simple.
And this square box is called a memory cell because this hidden state is actually containing
the short term memory. Now if you want to remember long term memory, we need to introduce
another state called long term memory. So that state is called C. So there are two states.
Now hidden state, which is short term memory. And there is a self state, which is a long term memory.
And we'll look into this in detail how exactly this will work.
But going back to our short term memory cell in traditional RNN,
it looks something like this. So I have drawn the vertical neurons here, but you can draw them
in a horizontal fashion as well. So it's just a layer of neurons in your ST and ST are vectors.
So when you have a word, for example, you will first convert into a vector.
Vector is nothing but a list of numbers. And your hidden state will be also a vector.
And using both these vectors, you will do, you know, like sigma operation, like a weighted
multiplication and then you apply activation function, which is which is tan h in the case of RNN.
And then you get a new hidden state. So here is a simplistic example.
So here you have tan h, you have weighted some going on. And this is how the short term memory cell
looks in traditional RNN. In LSTM, we are going to introduce a new cell state for a long term memory.
So let's say there is this cell state, okay. Now let's see how exactly this works by looking at
one more example. I love eating someosa by the way. So I have one more sentence for you to
autocomplete. Can you tell me what would you put here at dot dot dot? Well obviously,
Indian, Somosa is an Indian cuisine. So you will say his favorite cuisine is Indian.
Now take a pause and think about this. When is a human, when you make this case,
when you are processing the sentence, which words told you that this will be an Indian cuisine?
Well, it is this word, Somosa. If I didn't have Somosa here, if I had just had eats or every day,
it, so based on these words you can't guess, it is an Indian cuisine, right? There is some keywords.
If you are doing a movie review, for example, you are looking for keywords like, okay, excellent or
you know, terrible movie or amazing, the hero performed very well. So you are just looking
for specific words and the remaining words you can actually ignore. Now let's see how our traditional
RN would behave for this sentence. So traditional RNN, which is like, Amit Khan of Gusni,
having short term memory. When you feed all these words, it can remember only let's say last
two words. In reality RNNs can remember more words, but I'm just giving a simple example,
you know, just explain this concept. So let's say they have short term memory, just remember
only two words. So when you are at this sentence, almost for example, it remembers almost and the
Samosa, like the two words, last two words. When you are at here, cuisine is, it will
remember is and cuisine. So at this point, it doesn't have a knowledge of Samosa. So then for
traditional RNN, it is hard to make a guess that the cuisine is Indian. What if we build this
long term memory, along with short term memory, in such a way that we store the meaningful words
or the key words into this long term memory. So when I feed the world or each, it will not
store it. This is a blank string. It will not store it in a long term memory, but when you find things
like Samosa, it will store it in a long term memory. See Samosa, when you get almost, almost
is also not important. So I just store Samosa here. And when I go all the way here, now when I have
to make a prediction on cuisine, I have the memory that we are talking about Samosa and hands
it has to be Indian. Let's look at a little more complicated example.
Here, while I love Indian cuisine, my brother, Bobbin, Lowe's, which cuisine do you have any guess?
If you read the sentence carefully, you will figure it is an Italian cuisine. And you made that
decision based on the two keywords, which were pastas and cheese. So again, you are reading the sentence
and you are keeping some keywords in memory and throwing everything out like and that means
these are not important. For you, the important keywords are pastas and cheese.
Based on that, you make a decision that it is an Italian cuisine. So going back to our
R&N with long term memory. When you encounter, let's say Samosa used to or Samosa in your long term memory.
But you will keep on storing Samosa until you encounter pastas. So now the moment you encounter
pastas, you need to forget the previous long term memory, which is Samosa. So here, I threw
that thing out and I have new memory, which is pastas. And then you keep on preserving this until
you hit cheese. So when you hit cheese, you need to add that. So now you can't ignore pastas.
You need to add cheese on top of it. And then in then, when you are about to be asked,
what is your answer for autocomplete, you will say Italian because you have the memory of pastas and
cheese. Now you would ask me, how do you make this decision? How do you let's say when cheese comes,
you don't discard pastas. But when pastas comes, you discard Samosa. Well, all of this happens
during the training process. So when you are training your R&N, you are not giving only this
particular statement. This is this is a statement for prediction. When the training is happening,
you are giving thousands and thousands of such statements, which will build that understanding in R&N
on what to discard and what to store. So here we learnt a very important concept. So when you're
talking about LSTM or a long short term memory cell, so each of these cells are LSTM cells.
The first most important thing is the forget get. So the role of forget get is when you come
at this word pasta, it knows that it has to discard Samosa. So this is how forget get looks like.
So I have just expanded that cell, XT is a one word, you know, you process centers one word by one
and T is the timestamp. So that's why XT. So when you feed pastas into this forget get.
So the forget get is simple. You have previous hidden state. You take the current input, which is a
current word and you apply sigmoid function. Now you know that sigmoid function restricts your number
between 0 and 1. So it will if it has to discard the previous memory, it will output a vector,
which will have all 0s or all the values which are close to 0. And when you multiply that with
previous memory, which is previous cell state, you know you have a vector of less all 0s here
and you have another vector, which is a memory of previous cell state. The multiplication will of course
be 0 because you have discarded the previous memory, you know when this new word appeared.
So this is what a forget get looks like. So here you forgot about Samosa. Now there is another
thing which is an input get. So when pastas came, not only you forgot about Samosa, you need to add
a memory of pastas. So the way it will work is you will use sigmoid and tan h both on these two vectors.
So when you are doing by the way these vectors will have weight here. So there will be some weight
here, some weight here. So in this function what you are doing is ht minus 1 into that weight plus
xt into that weight plus bias and then you are applying tan h on top of it. And it's the same
equation here, the only difference is instead of tan h you are using sigmoid function.
And you multiply both of this output and then add that as a memory for this word.
The third one is output get. So in the output get, again you are doing weighted sum of hidden state
nxt and applying sigmoid function. Whatever is the output you take that and then you take long-term
memory, apply tan h and you multiply that and you will get your hidden state. So this will be your
hidden state. There are cases like length lesser the sentence autocomplete case that we are looking
at there is no variety actually. The state is carried using the short term memory. But
you know if there is a tan like a named entity recognition, there you need variety which is an output
and that output is same as ht. I mean you might apply sigmoid not sigmoid but let's say soft
max type of function here. But other than that it is kind of similar to ht. So now if you think about
the long term memory. So long term memory look at this line, look at this highway for example.
It has two things. Forget get an input to get. So forget get is like it will help you
forget things like simos or when pasta comes in and the input get will add new things into
memory. Like meaningful things you want to add in the memory. If it is a movie review you want to
add like horribile or amazing beautiful those kind of words. You know is the there are so many
words you don't care about. So that's what this LSTM will do and I'm going to refer you to a nice
article. I personally found this article to be very useful. I'm going to link in a video description
below. I did not mention any mathematical equation because you can use this article for any
here they explain how CT is calculated in terms of math formulas. So look at all math formulas.
Again I suggest you read this article properly because I myself have learned a lot from this and I
hope you found this video useful. If you did please give it a thumbs up share it with your friends.
I think this this can provide you a simple explanation of LSTM and in the
coming videos will be doing coding on LSTM will also be going over GRU in the future videos.
All right so till then thank you very much and bye.